Register to The Henry Gilbert Papers
Yale University Music Library
The Henry Gilbert Papers
1821-1980
MSS 35
Yale University Music Library
37.2
(93 boxes)
Music, correspondence and other papers, photographs, and additional materials by and about the American composer Henry Gilbert (1868-1928)
Gilbert, Henry F. B. (Henry Franklin Belknap), 1868-1928
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Some of the materials may be stored at the Library's off-campus shelving facility, so researchers should allow at least two business days to have the appropriate boxes paged.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Henry Gilbert Papers were established in the Music Library of Yale University by Mr. and Mrs. Philip C. Horton in 1968.
Arrangement
In 14 series as follows: I. Music. II. Music by Others. III. Correspondence. IV. Clippings. V. Programs. VI. Scrapbooks. VII. Financial and Legal Items. VIII. Musical Games. IX. Writings. X. Biographical Material. XI. Photographs. XII. Engraver's Plates. XIII. Sound Recordings. XIV. Miscellaneous Items.
Scope and Contents
The Henry Gilbert Papers contain manuscript and published music by Gilbert and others, correspondence, clippings, programs, scrapbooks, financial and legal items, musical games, writings by Gilbert and others, biographical material, photographs, and miscellaneous items. Their dates range from 1821 to 1980; most were created between the late nineteenth century and Gilbert's death in 1928.
The largest series in the Papers is music. There are manuscript and published musical works by Gilbert covering several genres: opera and incidental, orchestra, band, chamber and instrumental, songs, voice and instrumental ensemble, choral, and keyboard. The subseries Music by Others contains Gilbert's arrangements and transcriptions of music by others; manuscript and published works by his father, Benjamin Franklin Gilbert (1828-1894), and uncle, James L. Gilbert; and miscellaneous music by others.
The bulk of the correspondence is from others to Gilbert, spanning from 1885 to 1928. It includes letters from many of Gilbert's contemporaries in music and literature, such as Percy Atherton, Joseph Breil, Clarence Birchard, Charles Wakefield Cadman, John Alden Carpenter, George Whitefield Chadwick, Robert W. Chanler, Frederick W. Converse, Oscar Coon, Edward S. Curtis, Arthur Farwell, Lawrence Gilman, Henry Hadley, Maud Cuney Hare, Edward Burlingame Hill, Otto Kahn, Edgar Stillman Kelley, Serge Koussevitzky, Charles Martin Loeffler, Edward and Marian MacDowell, Frederick Manley, Ivan Narodny, George Turner Phelps, Edwin Carty Ranck, Edward Arlington Robinson, Thomas P. Robinson, Carl Ruggles, César Saerchinger, Bertram Shapleigh, Cecil Sharp, Arthur Shepherd, Alexander Smallens, Walter F. Spalding, Carl Stoeckel, the Wa-Wan Press, and Arthur Whiting. The correspondence from Gilbert to others consists of about 400 copies of typed letters and drafts from 1891 to 1928. There are also about 250 letters between Gilbert and his family dating from 1881 to 1927. Two subseries concern Gilbert's collaboration with Edward S. Curtis (1911-1920) and his association with the New Music Society of America (1906). The remainder of the correspondence is mostly between Gilbert's wife, Helen Kalischer Gilbert, and one of his daughters, Tessie Gilbert Horton, and others.
Henry Gilbert invented several musical games, which he had patented. The games, their instructions, and patents are included among the Papers.
There are about fifty lectures and articles by Gilbert, mostly in manuscript, pertaining to music as well as other subjects. Also included are twenty-nine of Gilbert's diaries and address books from 1882 until 1928. Gilbert's notebooks bridge his childhood to adulthood (1875-1927). There are thirty-five notebooks which include notes for music as well as school, thoughts and ideas, natural history, minerals, and butterflies.
Five photograph albums contain photographs of Gilbert, his family, and friends. The album dating from 1904-1925 contains photographs from the MacDowell Colony of people such as Aaron Copland, Mabel Daniels, Edward Burlingame Hill, Edgar Stillman Kelley, Marian MacDowell, Edwin Carty Ranck, and Edward Arlington Robinson. There are also over three hundred loose photographs of Gilbert and others.
Among the miscellaneous items are two oil portraits by Robert W. Chanler and Frank Waldo Murray and a plaster death mask of Gilbert.
The bulk of the Henry F. Gilbert Papers consists of five gifts from Mr. and Mrs. Philip C. Horton (Gilbert's daughter and her husband): December 27, 1968 (3 boxes); July 3, 1969 (20 boxes); December 18, 1976 (6 boxes, including the papers of Benjamin Franklin Gilbert and James L. Gilbert); December 18, 1978 (2 boxes); and May 27, 1981 (17 boxes, a suitcase, and a violin case). Mr. Philip Horton gave the Yale University Music Library for deposit, 21 boxes and loose items, including two portraits, on November 9, 1982.
Biographical / Historical
Henry Franklin Belknap Gilbert was born in Somerville, Massachusetts, on September 26, 1868. He had a congenital heart defect known as tetrology of Fallot and made medical history by outliving any other recorded sufferer by twenty-three years. Despite his poor health and chronic lack of funds, Gilbert achieved distinction as a composer, lecturer, editor, and writer.
Gilbert came from a musical family, and he studied violin, piano, theory, and composition at the New England Conservatory and with a variety of private teachers, including Edward MacDowell. As a young man he struggled to support himself by playing the violin and working in a variety of non-musical jobs. In 1893 he attended the Chicago World's Fair, where he had the opportunity to hear Asian and African music, which made a profound impression on him. In 1894, 1901, and 1927 he visited Europe. From 1902 to 1911 Gilbert collaborated with Arthur Farwell on the Wa-Wan Press, an important publisher of American music. In 1912 Gilbert spent the first of several summers at the MacDowell Colony, the last being in 1926.
In both his compositions and his writings, Gilbert was an influential proponent of musical nationalism. He believed that American composers should not rely solely on European models, but instead should draw inspiration from indigenous sources, such as the music of black Americans and American Indians. Gilbert's music frequently borrowed melodies and rhythms from ragtime, spirituals, and folk songs. Gilbert also transcribed Indian music from wax cylinders recorded by Edward S. Curtis for Curtis's book The North American Indian. These transcriptions are included in the Papers.
Several of Gilbert's works received major performances. Negro Rhapsody was commissioned for and performed at Norfolk, Connecticut in 1913. His Comedy Overture on Negro Themes was chosen to be performed in Russia by Glazunov and conducted by Glière in 1914. Riders to the Sea was performed by the New York Philharmonic in 1917. Gilbert's one-act opera Dance in Place Congo was performed by the Metropolitan Opera Ballet and Orchestra in 1918, and two years later it was rendered as an orchestral piece by the Boston Symphony Orchestra under Monteux. Gilbert composed the music to the first episode of the Pilgrim Tercentenary Pageant (1921). Other composers who contributed to the pageant were Clifton, Converse, Foote, Hill, Kelley, and Sowerby. In 1922 Gilbert wrote the film score to a documentary drama about whaling entitled Down to the Sea in Ships. The Boston Symphony Orchestra under Koussevitzky performed Gilbert's Symphonic Piece in 1926. Despite failing health, in 1927 Gilbert traveled to Frankfurt along with Copland to represent modern music in America at the ISCM Festival where his Dance in Place Congo was performed. Finally, his Nocturne was performed two months prior to his death by the Philadelphia Orchestra under Monteux.
Henry Gilbert died on May 19, 1928 in Cambridge, Massachusetts.
Composers -- Correspondence; Music -- United States -- 19th century; Music -- United States -- 20th Century; Operas -- Scores; Orchestral music -- Scores; Piano music; Songs; Atherton, Percy Lee, 1871-1944; Ayres, Frederic, 1876-1926; Barlow, Howard, 1892-1972; Bloch, Ernest, 1880-1959; Bodanzky, Artur, 1877-1939; Breil, Joseph Carl, 1870-1926; Cadman, Charles Wakefield, 1881-1946; Carpenter, John Alden, 1876-1951; Chadwick, G. W. (George Whitefield), 1854-1931; Clapp, Philip Greeley, 1888-1954; Clifton, Chalmers, 1889-1966; Converse, F. S. (Frederick Shepherd), 1871-1940; Coolidge, Elizabeth Sprague, 1864-1953; Coon, Oscar; Cuney-Hare, Maud, 1874-1936; Curtis, Edward S., 1868-1952; Damrosch, Walter, 1862-1950; Darrell, R. D. (Robert Donaldson), 1903-1988; Diaghilev, Serge, 1872-1929; Donovan, Richard, 1891-1970; Downes, Olin, 1886-1955; Dunn, James; Dykema, Peter W. (Peter William), 1873-1951; Eastman, George, 1854-1932; Engel, Carl, 1883-1944; Farnsworth, Charles Hubert, 1859-1947; Farwell, Arthur, 1872-1952; Fiedler, Max, 1859-1939; Fletcher, Alice C. (Alice Cunningham), 1838-1923; Flood, William H. Grattan (William Henry Grattan), 1859-1928; Foote, Arthur, 1853-1937; Freer, Eleanor Everest, 1864-1942; Gatti-Casazza, Giulio, 1869-1940; Gilbert, Benjamin Franklin, 1828-1894; Gilbert, Helen Kalischer; Gilbert, Henry F. B. (Henry Franklin Belknap), 1868-1928; Gilbert, J. L. (James L.); Gilman, Lawrence, 1878-1939; Glière, Reinhold Morit͡sevich, 1875-1956; Gray, H. W. (Harold Willard), 1868-1950; Griffes, Charles Tomlinson, 1884-1920; Hadley, Henry, 1871-1937; Hale, Philip, 1854-1934; Harmati, Sandor, 1892-1936; Heilman, William Clifford; Henderson, W. J. (William James), 1855-1937; Hill, Edward Burlingame, 1872-1960; Hughes, Rupert, 1872-1956; Humiston, William Henry, 1869-1923; Ives, Charles, 1874-1954; Jackson, George Pullen, 1874-1953; Jacobi, Frederick, 1891-1952; Kahn, Otto H., 1867-1934; Kelley, Edgar Stillman, 1857-1944; Kindler, Hans, 1892-1949; Koussevitzky, Serge, 1874-1951; Krehbiel, Henry Edward, 1854-1923; Langley, Allan Lincoln, 1892-1949; Lilienthal, Abraham Wolf, 1859-1928; Loeffler, Charles Martin, 1861-1935; MacDowell, Edward, 1860-1908; MacDowell, Marian, 1857-1956; Manley, Frederick; Martens, Frederick Herman, 1874-1932; Mason, Daniel Gregory, 1873-1953; Mengelberg, Willem, 1871-1951; Monteux, Pierre, 1875-1964; Narodny, Ivan, 1869-1953; Neuendorff, Adolf, 1843-1897; Ormandy, Eugene, 1899-1985; Parker, Horatio W. (Horatio William), 1863-1919; Patterson, Frank, 1871-1966; Phelps, George Turner; Rabaud, Henri, 1873-1949; Reiner, Fritz, 1888-1963; Robinson, Edwin Arlington, 1869-1935; Ruggles, Carl, 1876-1971; Saerchinger, César, 1889-1971; Schelling, Ernest, 1876-1939; Schwerké, Irving, 1893-1975; Shapleigh, Bertram, 1871-1940; Sharp, Cecil J. (Cecil James), 1859-1924; Shepherd, Arthur, 1880-1958; Slonimsky, Nicolas, 1894-1995; Smallens, Alexander, 1889-1972; Smith, David Stanley, 1877-1949; Sonneck, O. G. (Oscar George), 1873-1928; Spalding, Walter Raymond, 1865-1962; Stoeckel, Carl, 1858-1925; Stokowski, Leopold, 1882-1977; Stransky, Josef, 1872-1936; Taylor, Deems, 1885-1966; Toscanini, Arturo, 1867-1957; Varèse, Edgard, 1883-1965; Whiting, Arthur, 1861-1936
- Music, 1891-1927; Series I; 11.9' (20 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  MUSIC contains musical works by Gilbert arranged alphabetically within subseries by genre:
  A. Opera and Incidental
  B. Orchestra
  C. Band
  D. Chamber and Instrumental
  E. Songs
  F. Voice and Instrumental Ensemble
  G. Choral
  H. Keyboard
  I. Miscellaneous
  - School song books
  - Sketchbooks
  - Transcriptions and arrangements of North American Indian music and folk songs
  - Studies and exercises
  - Miscellaneous unidentified sketches
  General
  The index gives access by title.
  Box and folder numbers are not repeated for items in the same folder or box. There are some unfoldered items with box numbers but without folder numbers. Cross-references have been made from parts of works to the title under which they are described. Transcription of the title page is given only when it contains information not stated in the uniform title.
  Gilbert occasionally used the pseudonyms "Belknap" or "Hank."
  - Opera and Incidental, I.A
    - [Asia] Dance, 1 sheet; 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Holograph signed, in ink.
      Cymbalom part.
    - [Asia] Prometheus unbound Act II / [words by] P.B. Shelley, 1 score (7 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Holograph signed, in ink with pencil additions.
      For voice and piano.
    - [Asia (Sketches)]
      - [Asia (Sketches)], Loose sheets ([46] p.). (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Holographs in ink and pencil.
        Includes [5] loose sheets of analysis of works by Beethoven, Dvorák, Grieg, and Schumann.
      - [Asia (Sketches)], 7 p. of music; 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Holograph in ink and pencil.
        Includes 1 sheet labeled "Orchestration notes on Asia" by Henry Gilbert.
      - [Asia (Sketches)], Loose sheets ([11] p.); 30, 25 x 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Holographs in pencil.
    - Cathleen ni Houlihan
      See: Suite of Irish melodies.
    - [Down to the sea in ships. Town Crier] "Town crier": motive, [1] p.; 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Holograph in ink with pencil additions.
    - [Down to the sea in ships. Town Crier] "#66 Town Crier", [1] p. of music; 33 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Holograph in pencil and ink.
    - [Fantasy in Delft] Opera in one act / words by Thomas P. Robinson
      - [Fantasy in Delft] Opera in one act / words by Thomas P. Robinson, 1 score (341 p.), bound; 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Holograph signed, in ink, words in red ink.
        At end: "Fini. 6-19. '20 A.F.T."
      - [Fantasy in Delft] Opera in one act / words by Thomas P. Robinson, 1 score (339 p.); 33 cm. (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
        Holograph in pencil, words in red ink.
      - [Fantasy in Delft] Opera in one act / words by Thomas P. Robinson, 1 vocal score (159 p.), bound; 33 cm. (Box 2, Folder 6)
        The libretto (a-f, 32 p. - typescript) bound in front.
        Watercolor illustration of the characters on page c.
    - [Fantasy in Delft (Sketches)]
      - [Fantasy in Delft (Sketches)], 1 vocal score (pp. 1-23, 15(= 23)-124, [4]); 36 cm. (Box 1, Folder 7)
        Holograph in pencil.
      - [Fantasy in Delft (Sketches)], Loose sheets ([48] p.). (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Holographs in pencil and ink.
    - [Fantasy in Delft. Libretto]
      - [Fantasy in Delft. Libretto], 32 sheets; 28 cm. (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Typescript in black and red ink with corrections in pencil and additions in ink pasted on.
      - [Fantasy in Delft. Libretto], 30 sheets; 29 cm. (Box 1, Folder 10)
        Typescript in black and red ink.
    - [Fantasy in Delft. Synopsis] (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - [Fantasy in Delft. Synopsis], 4 sheets; 28 cm.
        Typescript with additions in ink and note on back from "Ma" to "Elizabeth."
        Includes carbon copy without additions or note.
      - [Fantasy in Delft. Synopsis], [1] sheet; 28 cm.
        Typescript with pencil corrections.
        "Story of play."
    - [Intimate story of Indian tribal life] (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Holographs and manuscript in ink.
      Numbers added later (orange pencil).
      Missing numbers 1, 10, 14-15.
      - No. 2 - Snake dance, 1 score (4 p.); 36 cm.
        For violin and piano.
      - No. 3 - Evening in Hopi land, 1 score (5 p.); 36 cm.
        For violin (?) and piano.
      - No. 4 - Woman dancer with skulls, 1 score ([3] p.); 35 cm.
        For B-flat clarinet, cornets, violins, violoncello, bass, rattle, and drum.
      - No. 5 - Lullaby, 1 score ( [3] p.); 34 cm.
      - No. 6 - By the arrow, 1 score ([2] p.); 36 cm.
      - No. 7 - Signal fire to the mountain god, 1 score ([2] p.); 36 cm.
      - No. 8 - Cañon de Chelly, 1 score ([4] p.); 35 cm.
      - No. 9 - Sunset in Navaho land, 1 score ([3] p.); 36 cm.
      - No. 11 - Sun dance, 1 score ([4] p.); 36 cm.
      - No. 12 - Cheyenne watering scene, 1 score ([4] p.); 36 cm.
      - No. 13 - Sioux war party, 1 score (3 p.); 36 cm.
      - No. 16 - Wahgh dancing, 1 score ([3] p.); 35 cm.
        For piano.
      - No. 17 - Song of the wolf, 1 score ([1] p.); 36 cm.
        Arrangement of orchestra score?
      - No. 18 - Hopi lullaby, 1 score ([2] p.); 35 cm.
      - No. 19 - Canoe paddling, 1 score ([3] p.); 35 cm.
      - No. 20 - Canoe song, 1 score ([3] p.); 35 cm.
      - No. 21 - Sitting Bull war song, 1 score (2 p.); 27 x 36 cm.
      - Iroquois tune used in the Dream of the Ancient Red Man, [2] p. of music; 36 cm.
      - Sketch labeled "actual nubs (F.C.).", [1] p. of music; 33 cm.
    - [Intimate story of Indian tribal life (Sketches)]
      - [Intimate story of Indian tribal life (Sketches)], Loose sheets ([ca. 88] p.); 36 cm. (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - [Intimate story of Indian tribal life (Sketches)], Loose sheets ([7] p.); 46 cm. (Box 92, Folder 14)
    - [Intimate story of Indian tribal life. Scenario], [15] sheets; 28 cm. (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Typescript with markings by Henry Gilbert.
      Contents: Sunset in Navajo land - The night scout - By the arrow - Offering the skull - On the shores of the North Pacific - Cañon de Chelly - On the Jocko (two copies) - Evening in Hopi land - Two untitled texts, and outlines for the "Southwest" and "Northwest" lectures. Also includes a sheet labeled "Memo of work done by [Oscar?] Coon."
      See also: H. Keyboard. Intimate story... Indian scenes; arr.
    - [Pilgrim Tercentenary Pageant]
      - Suite from Pilgrim Tercentenary Pageant, 1 score (49 p.), bound; 56 cm. (Box 92; 2, Folder 15; 16)
        At end: "A.F.T. Boston, Mass. 11-23-2l."
        "Copyright, 1921, by Henry F. Gilbert" - p. 1.
        Portion of a package wrapper with notes laid in folder.
        Contents: I. Prelude and Norse Scene - II. (a) French and Indian pantomime - (b) Indian dance - (c) Pestilence.
      - Pilgrim Tercentenary Pageant: First episode, 1 score (38, A-M p.); 47 cm. (Box 2, Folder 17)
        Holograph signed, in pencil and ink.
        Contents: Prelude - Pantomime - Pestilence music.
      - Pilgrim Tercentenary Pageant: First episode, 1 score (30, 6, 8, a-f p.); 33-47 cm. (Box 2, Folder 18)
        Contents: I. Norse scene - II. French and Indian Pantomime - II (b) Indian dance - Pestilence.
      - Suite: from Pilgrim Tercentenary Pageant, 62 parts; 34 cm. (Box 2, Folder 19-20, Box 3, Folder 21-24)
        Manuscript or holograph (?) signed, in ink.
    - [Pirate opera? (Sketches)], Loose sheets ([23] p.); 21-32 cm. (Box 3, Folder 25)
      Title from folder labeled: "Pirate opera (?) Tentative sketches, particles, motives."
    - [Pot of broth (Sketches)] (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - 1st Beggar's song, [1] sheet of music; 34 cm.
        Holograph in ink.
        Incomplete.
      - 2nd - Beggar's song, [1] p. of music; 34 cm.
    - [Riders to the sea] Symphonic prologue: to J.M. Synge's drama. - New York: G. Schirmer, c1919.
      - [Riders to the sea] Symphonic prologue: to J.M. Synge's drama. - New York: G. Schirmer, c1919., 1 score (31 p.); 35 cm. (Box 3, Folder 27)
        2 copies, with pencil markings.
      - [Riders to the sea] Symphonic prologue: to J.M. Synge's drama. - New York: G. Schirmer, c1919., Proof sheets for the above score; 36 cm. (Box 3, Folder 28)
        Contains many additions by Henry Gilbert in ink and pencil.
    - [Riders to the sea] Prelude
      - [Riders to the sea] Prelude, 1 score (25 p.) (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - [Riders to the sea] Prelude, 9 parts; 35 cm. (Box 3, Folder 30)
        Holographs in ink.
        Includes: flute, clarinet, cornet, piano, violin I, violoncello, bass, and unidentified part.
    - [Riders to the sea (Sketches)], Loose sheets ([67] p.); 34-36 cm. (Box 3, Folder 31)
      See also: H. Keyboard. Riders to the sea; arr.
    - Story of a vanishing race
      See: A. Opera and Incidental. Intimate story of Indian tribal life; and H. Keyboard. Intimate story ... Indian scenes; arr.
    - [Suite of Irish melodies]
      - [Suite of Irish melodies], 8 parts; 34 cm. (Box 3, Folder 32)
        Contents: I. Lament: O white maive - II. Carolan's devotion. II. Give me your hand- III. Plangsty. Jig (Reel laid in).
      - Miscellaneous pieces in envelope labeled "Suite of Irish melodies" with the above parts. (Box 3, Folder 33)
        Includes:
        - The battle of Argan Mór: in the time of Ossian, [1] sheet of music; 34 cm.
        - #46, #86, #139, and #147 (Bunting), [5] p. of music; 34 cm.
        - The coolin, [1] sheet of music; 34 cm.
        - Irish jig, [1] sheet of music; 34 cm.
        - The maiden, [1] sheet of music; 34 cm.
        - #10, 14, 49, 246, 288 (Petrie), [6] sheets of music; 34 cm.
    - [Uncle Remus]
      Sheets with notes laid in.
      - Act I. No. 1.: Prologue and Br. Rab. Serenade, 12 sheets of music; 33 cm. (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Act I. No. 2 (Sketch), [2] p. of music; 24 x 32 cm. (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - Act I. No. 5, 1 score (9 p.); 34 cm. (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - Act I. No. 8 (T [ar] B[aby] Episode) [finale], 10 sheets of music; 34 cm. (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - Act II. No. 4, [3] p. of music; 34 cm. (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Fox, 1 score ([1] sheet); 34 cm. (Box 3, Folder 39)
        Holograph in ink, words in pencil.
        Incomplete sketch.
      - Act III: For legend (animal) [possibly finale to Jamboree], 1 score (8 p.); 34 cm. (Box 3, Folder 40)
        Holograph in ink, with words in pencil.
      - [When the wolf lies down with the lamb! (Sketch)], 1 score ([6] p.); 34 cm. (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - Animal dance, [4] p. of music; 27 x 36 cm. (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - [Uncle Remus (Sketches)], Loose sheets ([105] p.); 10-36 am. (Box 4, Folder 43-45)
      Three sheets with notes re sketches laid in.
      Sketch of piano piece "Humoreski" lain in.
    - [Uncle Remus. Libretto], 20 sheets; 28 cm. (Box 4, Folder 46)
      Typescript and 2 copies.
      Libretto by Charles Johnston.
    - [Uncle Remus. Libretto] Prologue and scenario, 2, 3 p.; 28 cm. (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - [Uncle Remus. Scenario], [1], 2, 19 p.; 28 cm. (Box 4, Folder 48)
      Typescript and 2 copies, original with pencil note.
      Includes 5 extra sheets and folder with notes.
      See also: B. Orchestra. American dances and comedy overture on negro Themes; D. Chamber and Instrumental. Tempo di rag; and H. Keyboard. American dances; arr., Comedy overture on negro themes; arr. and Negro dances; arr.
    - Unidentified opera (Sketch), Loose sheets (13 p.); 35 cm. (Box 4, Folder 49)
      Characters include: Sallusti, Gadiel, Ruy, and Don S.
  - Orchestra, I.B
    - Americanesque
      See: Humoresque.
    - [American dances]
      - [American dances], 1 score (46 p.), bound; 34 cm. (Box 4, Folder 50)
        Holograph signed, in ink with pencil markings.
        "New York: H.W. Gray" - cover.
      - [American dances], 44 parts; 35 cm. (Box 4, Folder 51-54)
        Manuscript in ink.
    - [American dances (Sketches)], 1 score ([39] p.); 46 cm. (Box 92, Folder 55-57)
      Oversize.
      See also: A. Opera and Incidental. Uncle Remus.
    - [Comedy overture on negro themes]
      - [Comedy overture on negro themes], 1 score (51 p.), bound; 31 cm. (Box 4, Folder 58)
      - [Comedy overture on negro themes], Proof sheets for the above score; 33 cm. (Box 4, Folder 59)
        Contains many jottings and corrections in Henry Gilbert's hand.
        See also: A. Opera and Incidental. Uncle Remus; and H. Keyboard. Comedy overture ...; arr.
    - [Dance] Dance - fantasie, 1 score (39 p.); 35 cm. (Box 5, Folder 60)
      "Sketches for Washington Comp. Dance movement original score" - folder.
    - [Dance (Sketches)], Loose sheets ([32] p.); 18-36 cm. (Box 5, Folder 61)